Guide to the Montana Juvenile Justice Advisory Council Records 1969-1974
Montana Historical Society
Montana Juvenile Justice Advisory Council Records
1969-1974
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 141
Montana Governor's Juvenile Justice Advisory Council
.7 linear feet of shelf space
This collection consists of records (1969-1974) kept by Justice Frank Haswell concerning his work with the Montana Juvenile Justice Advisory Council, including correspondence, financial records, minutes, reports, clippings, and miscellany. [Printed materials transferred to Library.]
The Montana Juvenile Justice Advisory Council was established by Governor Forrest Anderson in August 1972, to examine existing juvenile legislation and juvenile correctional facilities, and to recommend revisions in the law. Governor Anderson stressed the need to examine the constitutional rights of juveniles in light of a recent U.S. Supreme Court decision expanding those rights. Governor Anderson appointed Associate Justice Frank Haswell to head the Council and Doug Chase, Harold Hanser, Paul Hatfield, Jeremiah Johnson, Helen Kampfe, Mike McLean, Frank Sennett, John Thomas, and Robert Wilson as Council members. Terry Wallace and Steve Nelson were hired as staff. In April 1973 the Council published a discussion draft of its proposed Montana Youth Act and solicited comments from legal experts and the public. As a result of these comments the draft was revised and in November a second draft Montana Youth Act was published. Governor Thomas Judge re-appointed the Council in July 1973 to continue its work. As a result, two bills were introduced into the second session of the 43rd Legislative Assembly (1974): HB 797 to revise the law relating to abused, neglected, and dependent children; and HB 798, the Montana Youth Justice Act. Both passed into law.
This collection consists of records kept by Justice Frank Haswell on his work with the Juvenile Justice Advisory Council. It includes general correspondence (August 1972-June 1974); financial records; minutes (March-November 1973); reports (1973) including comments on the two proposed laws and studies of juvenile justice by legal experts; clippings; and miscellany including drafts of proposed sections of the law, research notes, etc. Printed materials were transferred to the Library.
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Courts--Montana; Juvenile delinquency--Montana; Juvenile justice, Administration of--Montana; Youth--Montana
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- General Correspondence
  - Chronological (correspondents include Governor Forrest H. Anderson, Governor's Crime Control Commission, National Council of Juvenile Court Judges, Board of Crime Control, Robert E. Sullivan, Montana Advisory Council on Children and Youth, Robert C. Sykes, Henry Loble, Mountain View School, interoffice memos), 1972 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Chronological (correspondents include Child Care Coordinating Council of Greater Helena, Montana Council of Churches, Board of Crime Control, Governor Thomas L. Judge, University of Colorado Center for Action Research, Lee Metcalf, Conrad B. Fredricks, Richard O. Shields, Judge Lester H. Loble Foundation, National Council of Juvenile Court Judges, Robert C. Sykes, Robert E. Sullivan, Helena Vocational-Technical Center, Paul G. Hatfield, Frank Haswell, interoffice memos), 1973 (Box-folder 1 / 2-3)
  - Chronological (correspondents include National Juvenile Law Center, Judge Lester H. Loble Foundation, Montana county Attorney's Association, Frank Haswell, Robert C. Sykes, interoffice memos), 1974 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
- Financial Records
  - Miscellaneous, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
- Minutes
  - Minutes of the Council, 1973 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
- Printed Material
  - List of out-of-state printed material used as references by Council, undated (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - List of printed material transferred to Library, undated (Box-folder 1 / 8)
- Reports
  - "Assumptions behind and structural requisites for a Youth Services System," by Robert M. Hunter, 1973 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - "A brief review of the correctional institutions serving Montana's delinquent youth", 1972 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Comments by consultants on an analysis of proposed Montana Youth Act, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - "Comparison of juvenile delinquency law" (among the states), circa 1972 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - "Juvenile Code revision," by Harry O. Lawson, 1969 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - "Report on consultation to the State of Montana Governor's Juvenile Justice Committee," by Harry O. Lawson and David R. Schmidt, 1973 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - "Subsidized adoption", undated (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - "Youth Development Bureau Conference, Helena, Montana" (final report), 1973 May (Box-folder 1 / 16)
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous (re appointment of Montana Juvenile and Delinquency Commission and work of Juvenile Justice Advisory Commission; includes one radio editorial), 1948, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
- Miscellany
  - "Billings-Yellowstone County Law Enforcement Consolidation Project: discussion and evaluation", 1973 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - "Changes to the Montana Youth Act draft on the basis of abused, neglected, and dependent child" (includes various versions of proposed law), 1973 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - "First final draft" (includes revisions) and "Second final draft" for proposed Montana Youth Act, 1973 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - "Governor's creation and record of the Juvenile Justice Advisory Council", 1973 July (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - "Juvenile institutions" report by Montana Legislative Council to 43rd Legislative Assembly, 1972 July (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - "Juvenile Justice Advisory Council publicity", 1973 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
  - List of members of Juvenile Justice Committee, undated (Box-folder 2 / 5)
  - Montana Board of Crime Control grant application, 1973 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Montana Institute for Juvenile Justice conference materials, undated (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Montana juvenile offender procedures charges, 1971, undated (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Notes (includes proposed meeting agendas, comments on sections of law, etc.), 1973 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
  - Proposed act re juvenile court probation services, 1972 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - Public meeting agendas on proposed Montana Youth Act, 1973 May (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Research materials (includes computer bibliographic search, historical background, etc.), 1971-1973, undated (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - Youth Consent to Medical Treatment Act (various draft versions), 1973 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
  - Youth Development Bureau Conference, Helena, packet, 1973 May (Box-folder 2 / 14)